<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cassius of Parma his Orpheus with Nathan Chitræus his commentarie, abridged into short notes: most profitable for the framing of the manners of schollers. Translated and abridged by Roger Rawlyns of Lyncolnes Inne, student in the common lawes.</title>
            <title>Orpheus. English</title>
            <author>Telesio, Antonio, 1482-1533?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1587</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13761</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118508</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853715</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853715</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19109</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13761)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19109)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 318:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cassius of Parma his Orpheus with Nathan Chitræus his commentarie, abridged into short notes: most profitable for the framing of the manners of schollers. Translated and abridged by Roger Rawlyns of Lyncolnes Inne, student in the common lawes.</title>
                  <title>Orpheus. English</title>
                  <author>Telesio, Antonio, 1482-1533?</author>
                  <author>Cassius, Caius, Parmensis, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Homer. Iliad. Book 23, 304-325. English. aut</author>
                  <author>Rawlyns, Roger.</author>
                  <author>Chytraeus, Nathan, 1543-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Printed by Thomas Orwin],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1587.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The attribution of "Orpheus" to Cassius Parmensis is spurious; it is in fact by Antonio Telesio.</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>"Nestor his Antilochus", a translation of the Iliad, XXIII, 304-25; and "Certaine generall conclusions concerning the condition of our common lawes .. By R.R. &amp;c." each have separate dated title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19109:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19109:1"/>
            <p>Caſsius of Parma his <hi>Orpheus: With</hi> Nathan Chitraeus <hi>his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie, abridged into ſhort notes: moſt</hi> profitable for the framing of the manners of Schollers.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated and abridged by <hi>Roger Rawlyns</hi> of <hi>Lyncolnes Inne,</hi> Student in the Common Lawes.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>At London. 1587.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19109:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19109:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lord, the Lord Robert Earle <hi>of</hi> Eſſex <hi>and</hi> Ewe, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icount</hi> Hereforde, and <hi>Bourghchier,</hi> Lord <hi>Ferrers</hi> of <hi>Chartley, Bourghchier,</hi> and <hi>Louayne, Master of the</hi> Queenes Maieſties Horſe, and Knight of the moſt noble Order of the Garter: <hi>Roger Rawlyns</hi> wiſheth the true felicitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable, whereas Loue among men, was ſometimes of ſo great accompt, as the ſame hath been taken to be the firſt and chief cauſe of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and not vtilitie, (as affirmeth the learned <hi>Scot</hi>) which enforced men by a naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct to communicate their priuate labors to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like vſe, being for ſuch their loue, requited with the loue of thoſe, whom they did ſo benefite. Now, the matter is cleane contrarie: for who is more miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of the worſt, which are the most, than he that ſtudieth moſt to common profite? Which conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as it hath been one hinderance to me in my Studie (the more is my fault) ſo is it the cauſe, why I purpoſe to ſuppreſſe, to the vſe only of my priuate friends, that, which otherwiſe, I could be contented ſhould bee common. And although they can by no meanes occupie either their Senſe, or Reaſon, but the ſame will leade them perforce vnto a thankefull remembrance of our fathers, who haue by cunning, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ordered the nature, or inuented, or ordered the qualities of things, in a moſt pleaſant courſe: yet they themſelues haue no care, to practize in the like manner, for their owne eaſe, and helpe of their posteritie: ſuffering their knowledge gotten in the time of their life, to depart with their laſt breath: And ſome more vnlouing than others, neither will themſelues, neither will they without reproches, ſuffer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to labour in like practizes of <hi>Arte,</hi> ſeeming of condition, ſomewhat like the man, that being cured of follie, was highlie offended, affirming, that he neuer liued ſo pleaſant a life, as when he was a foole. So as we may ſee (except it be in ſome men more Chriſtian than others) now, churliſhnes to ſucceede loue, vnthankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:19109:3"/>thankefulnes, follie, wiſedome: that being moſt true in the multitude, which <hi>luuenal</hi> ſaith of his times:
<q>
                  <l>The earth doth now bring foorth, of bodie ſmall</l>
                  <l>Bad men, of little wit, or none at all.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But to the Cauſe, the Scope, and Center of all my ſpeeches, that is, concerning the <hi>Arte,</hi> in ſtudying, or ordering the Common Lawes, as I neuer fainted in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the ſame may bee performed, and in what manner: as ſtaying my ſelfe vpon Principles, which of their owne nature are inexpugnable, and feare not the frowning of a Cenſurer. So doo I feare nothing more, than that I haue ſmall part in the ſame performance: for I am hindered in the meanes, which are ſaid to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to a Student of the Common Laws, that is, to be leade in his ſeate, to haue an yron head, and a golden purſe. For the firſt, how little time (of late) I haue ſate at it, they could be are me witnes, that haue been acquainted with my buſines. For the ſecond, how greatlie I haue been diſtracted, I my ſelfe knowe, <hi>Nec oſtentabo vulnera &amp; ſicatrices meas.</hi> For the third, my purſe was neuer ſo heauie, but that I could lift it without helpe. Moreouer, I finde with ſome griefe by obſeruation in other men, that he that practiſeth in any publike cauſe, (as <hi>Cardanus</hi> ſaith) ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to ſale his owne imperfections, his faults will ſwell in the eyes of his Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, he muſt ſubiect himſelfe to infamous ſlaunders, enuious reproches, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, which notwithſtanding ought againe of him to be contemned: <hi>Vt deriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res noſtros de ſumno quaſi deſpicientes, derideamus.</hi> Yet herein I doo content my ſelfe, as, he to deſcry land, whereunto the Pilot muſt guide the ſhip: or as a weake wretch, to giue aime vnto others, whoſe ſtrings I am not able to ſtirre, and whom I wiſh, may ſtrike the marke.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi> 
                  <date>this <hi>27.</hi> of September <hi>1587.</hi> From <hi>Crowne Court in Chauncery Lane.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors moſt humble</hi> Ro. Rawlyns.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19109:3"/>
            <head>ILLVSTRISSIMO DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino, Comiti Eſſexio, ſtudioſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum <hi>omnium Mecaenati, R. R. hanc</hi> Chartam (honoris cauſa) <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat conſecrátque.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Vi (obſecro) haec potiùs dicarem quàm tibi? qui nobilitate excellis,
<q>Nec ſinis ingenium nobilitate premi:</q>
Quare, Iuris meum Compendium non poteſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lùm meam in te obſeruantiam apud omnes te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtari, ſed etiam te huius ſanctiſſimae diſciplinae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monere: Sanctiſſimam diſciplinam appello, quia tecum loquor, cui non eſt ignota eius praeſtantia, &amp; diuinitas. Dubitarem ſanè ita loqui ſi cum ijs ſermo eſſet, qui, cùm artem ſibi neceſſariam igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, eos odio proſequuntur, à quibus intelligunt ſeeo nomine ſuperari: cupiúntque nulla eſſe iura, nullas leges, quo faciliùs ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio ſuo belluino omnia turbent. Sed, fremant, qui volunt, dicam quod ſentio. Praeſtat iudicandi ſcientia, iudicandi poteſtati, &amp; dignus igitur, qui praeſit iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio, praeſtat Iudici imperito. Haec omnia tu optimè ſcis. Itaque ad te libentèr ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niet ars illa, quae iudicandi normam tradit, quae diuinas, humanáſque res diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, quae omnes homines in officio continet, malos poenis coercet, bonos prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mijs afficit, &amp; (vt vno verbo dicam) humanam ſocietatem conſeruat. Inquit IV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVS PACIVS, Petro Saletano, epiſtola ſua, in quatuor libros Inſtitutionum, IMP. CAES. IVSTINIANI.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Tui honori deditiſſimus:</hi> R. Rawlyns.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19109:4"/>
            <head>To his louing Maſters and friends, the <hi>Students of Lyncolns Jnne, R. R. wiſheth</hi> profite and pleaſure in their ſtudies.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt beloued Gentlemen, I haue herein deſperatelie aduentured vpon your fauours, hoping that you will take affection for ſatisfaction, where iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is wanting for currant payment. If I haue offended through follie or imperfection, you may giue me thankes for that, becauſe therein is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed your wiſedome and patience, (as Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of himſelfe) <hi>wiſemen can eaſilie beare with fooles.</hi> If you ſhall iudge me of preſumption, (as the Prouerbe is, <hi>Sus Mineruam</hi>) why then (alas) pardon that too, I moſt hartelie pray you: for, I muſt confeſſe, (without flatterie) that I doo ſo much the more feare your cenſures, by how much the more I long after your goodwills. The beſt for me, is, that the price of my bookes is but your pardon and loue, which ye may giue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out coſt: and which if ye ſhall denie me, yet will I not ceaſe to loue you, and to cloy you with my countrey fruites.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt louing friend and ſeruant:</hi> Ro. Rawlyns.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:4"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Of</hi> Caſsius <hi>of</hi> Parma, <hi>the Author</hi> of this Fragment.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Oncerning the Author, it is thought that this was the very ſame man, of whom <hi>Horace</hi> maketh mention in the 1. of his <hi>Satyres,</hi> the 10. booke, verſe the 62. to this purpoſe:
<q>
                        <l>Not otherwiſe then when a man hath brought</l>
                        <l>His mind within the compaſſe of ſixe feete:</l>
                        <l>Pleaſde herewithall, or if his hand haue wrought</l>
                        <l>Two hundreth verſes, ere he goe to meate:</l>
                        <l>And after dinner, then as many moe:</l>
                        <l>Such was the wit of that Etrurian</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Caſſius,</hi> which as a running ſtreame did flowe:</l>
                        <l>So that a fire was made to burne this Man</l>
                        <l>Of his owne writings, as the fame doth goe.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And againe <hi>Horace</hi> maketh mention of <hi>Caſsius</hi> in the 1. booke, Epiſtle. 5. which he wrote to <hi>Albius Tibullus,</hi> the 3. verſe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Albius,</hi> O perfect Iudge of all our ſpeach,</l>
                     <l>What ſhould I ſay, that thou haſt now in hand?</l>
                     <l>Thou writeſt ſomewhat (that may ouerreach</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſſius</hi> his fragments) in the <hi>Pedan</hi> land.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>By which we may gather, that <hi>Caſsius</hi> was of no ſmall accompt, eſpeciallie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that were learned, and of iudgement.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of Orphëus.</head>
                     <p>Therefore did <hi>Caſsius</hi> (as it ſeemeth) giue this Pamphlet this inſcription of <hi>Orphëus,</hi> as in commendation of whoſe labour in Studie, and Continencie, all his verſes might be made. Of <hi>Orphëus, Plato</hi> maketh mention <hi>Booke</hi> 10. <hi>of his Commonwealth,</hi> where he faigneth, that <hi>Orphëus</hi> his ſoule (when he died) would not be borne againe of a woman, for the hatred which he bare to that Sexe, but did chooſe rather the life of a Swan, as <hi>Thamyris</hi> had done of a Nightingale.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Argument of this Booke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Caſsius</hi> of <hi>Parma,</hi> would by theſe verſes, as it were with the pencill of his wit, &amp; eloquence, expreſſe the likenes &amp; the patterne of a good and gentle <hi>Nature,</hi> contending to attaine the height and excellencie of learning and eloquence: and of ſuch a <hi>Nature,</hi> he doth firſt ſhew (not obſcurely) the ſignes, then the needfull helpes, next, what ſhould be done of boyes, and yong men, while they are yet in the floure of their age: and laſtly, what is by them to be auoyded, by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Orphëus,</hi> while he was yet but a yong man.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Caſſij Parmenſis Orphëus.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Arguta primùm cùm plectra parentis, &amp; auro</l>
                        <l>Diſtinctam ſumpſit citharam Rhodopëius heres,</l>
                        <l>Ridehan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſegnes pulſus, digitóſque micantes</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:19109:5"/>
                        <l>Serius, &amp; chordis indoctè diſſona vocis.</l>
                        <l>Mox pudor exardens, &amp; gloria dulcis honeſti,</l>
                        <l>Luſibus auertit puerilibus: omnis &amp; illùc</l>
                        <l>Pèrditus incumbens, Muſae pallebat amore.</l>
                        <l>Et nunc maternis inhiat, nunc ille paternis</l>
                        <l>Cantibus: hìnc illìnc diſcens dependet vtrin<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>.</l>
                        <l>Nulla Venus faciem coepit mentita doloſis</l>
                        <l>Compedibus: ſomni fuerat, parcus<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Lydi:</l>
                        <l>Donec, ridiculus dudùm, modulamine ſiluas,</l>
                        <l>Euulſos<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, ſuis ſcopulos radicibus egit:</l>
                        <l>Auſus &amp; ire vtam mortalibus inconceſſam,</l>
                        <l>Poenarum oblitos demulſit carmine manes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>"Non leuis adſcenſus, ſi quis petit ardua: ſudor</l>
                        <l>"Plurimus hunc tollit: nocturno ex ſomnis oliuo</l>
                        <l>"Immoritur: delet, quod mox laudauerat in ſe,</l>
                        <l>"Qui cupit aeterno donari frondis honore.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>The ſame Verſes engliſhed.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>When firſt the noble child of <hi>Rhodopy,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>His Parents quill, in tender hand gan hold,</l>
                        <l>Therewith to ſound his harpe of Iuory</l>
                        <l>Decked with lynes and asterisks of gold:</l>
                        <l>His ſingers drawled, and his ſtrokes were cold</l>
                        <l>With peering ioynts, wherewith they laugh, to ſee</l>
                        <l>How to the ſtrings his note did diſagree.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Straight ſhamefaſtnes enflaming with deſire</l>
                        <l>And glorious ſweetnes of ſo faire a thing,</l>
                        <l>From childiſh ſports, which yonger yeares require,</l>
                        <l>Doo turne him quite: hencefoorth to play and ſing</l>
                        <l>For life he plies: the loue whereof doth bring</l>
                        <l>Palenes of face: yet ſtill through earneſtnes</l>
                        <l>He hangs his iawe, while that with greedines</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>He heares his father, or his mother play:</l>
                        <l>On him, or her he liſtening doth depend</l>
                        <l>Euen at their lips, no painted wanton, gay</l>
                        <l>By borrowed hue, could force his heart to bend</l>
                        <l>Such guilefull giues a liking eye to lend.</l>
                        <l>Nor were his ſleepe and food outragious:</l>
                        <l>So that, now, he (lately ridiculous)</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Could cauſe the Rock to mooue, rent from the roote,</l>
                        <l>And woods draw neere, he plaid and ſang ſo well,</l>
                        <l>That daring goe, where els no mortall foote</l>
                        <l>Had trod: he ſtild the ſprites and ghoſts which dwell</l>
                        <l>Below, did eaſe from puniſhments of hell.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>"None eaſie clyming can preuaile to gaine</l>
                        <l>"Athing of woorth: it will be got with paine.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:19109:5"/>
                        <l>Which who deſires, that man endureth ſweate,"</l>
                        <l>Endangering his life through want of reſt,"</l>
                        <l>The <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aſting oyle, can prooue his labour great:"</l>
                        <l>What firſt he liked, now he doth deteſt,"</l>
                        <l>And blots that thing, which whilome pleaſde him beſt."</l>
                        <l>The man muſt, thus demeane himſelfe (I ſay)"</l>
                        <l>Who ſeekes the gift of neuer dying bay."</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Signes.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 Good Parents.</item>
                        <item>2 An alacritie, or naturall quicknes of wit.</item>
                        <item>3 To bluſh, or to be aſhamed of euill doing.</item>
                        <item>4 A deſire to balance the euill deede with greater poize of well doing.</item>
                        <item>5 A moderate diſpoſition to paſtime or playing.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Helpes.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 A good Teacher or Schoolemaſter, as here is ſuppoſed by <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liope,</hi> the Parents of <hi>Orphëus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 If the Parents being themſelues learned, doo teach and ouerſee the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their children, and ſo are not conſtrained to giue credite to ſome blinde Schoolemaſter, reaſoning with as little iudgement, as a blind man doth of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours.</item>
                        <item>3 A mutuall affection betweene the Scholler and the Maſter, ſo as the Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler doo beare a childlike loue to the Teacher, and the Teacher a fatherlike loue to the Scholler.</item>
                        <item>4 It helpes much oftentimes, if the child bee brought vp in the fathers voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with which, by ſeeing, and by hearing, euen from his cradle, he ſeemeth to be acquainted.</item>
                        <item>5 That he begin to be taught in due time, not too late, leaſt he prooue a loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer: nor too ſoone, leaſt he be at the firſt diſcouraged.</item>
                        <item>6 That the Teacher be not oftentimes changed: for, as Trees often remoued take no ſure roote in any ground: ſo children put from one Teacher to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, doo no great good any where.</item>
                        <item>7 That the Parents betweene themſelues doo not varie, either concerning the matter or manner of their childrens education, eſpeciallie in the hearing of their children, who will eaſilie take aduantage of ſuch controuerſies, and thereby, as in a doubt, whether they ſhall doo this thing, or that thing, they will not eaſilie applie themſelues vnto any thing.</item>
                        <item>8 That the inſtruments, meanes, or tooles of their vocation, be in moſt faire wiſe ordered, as that a Scholler haue his booke of a faire print, well bound, phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lited and ſpotted with gold, &amp;c. for herein are children much delighted.</item>
                        <item>9 That all bee begun, with the helpe of God, which is here inferred, becauſe that <hi>Apollo</hi> and <hi>Calliope,</hi> are ſaid to haue been accompted among the number of the heathen Gods.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Things to be done.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 The Scholler muſt nothing eſteeme to be derided of others, for deriſion is incident to all good beginnings.</item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:19109:6"/>
                        <item>2 He muſt not be diſcouraged, though the thing ſeene hard at the firſt to be learned: for, nothing is caſie at the firſt.</item>
                        <item>3 Though moderate recreation bee allowed, yet, he muſt not take it in too great meaſure: for, not wiſemen but ſooles keepe a continuall holiday.</item>
                        <item>4 Not many things, but onely one thing is to bee attempted for, one buſines of anie moment will require one whole man.</item>
                        <item>5 He muſt proſecute his attempted and purpoſed vocation with earneſt, and continuall labour: which, it is thought they doo, which are <hi>Louers of Enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes, of Paines, with heate and continuance.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6 He muſt bee a louer of learning: for, otherwiſe, bee his labour earneſt, and continuall, yet it is done againſt the wooll, for he performeth it with great cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</item>
                        <item>7 He muſt aske, and reſolue queſtions, he muſt loue commendations, and bee deſirous to finde out the trueth: that he bee readie to aske, heare, and put in practize the councells and reſolutions of his betters.</item>
                        <item>8 An exchaunge of his good endeuours, with others his equalls for their like endeuours, and a comparing of the ſame together, with an emulation and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to doo better, and with an amending of his owne doings.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Things to be auoyded.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 A phantaſie, or falſe opinion of his owne well doing.</item>
                        <item>2 Slacknes, which is, an intermiſſion, or negligent handling of his Studie: which is like vnto retchleſnes, which neither knoweth, nor attempteth any good thing. Sloath knowing, but, not vrging, nor bringing the thing knowne, to a good end, but deferring euerie thing to another day, by pretence of idle excuſes. Idlenes, which ſo performeth, that, as good neuer a whit, as neuer the better.</item>
                        <item>3 This nightly working, though it be here noted in <hi>Orphëus,</hi> yet is it not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie to be commended, but the day muſt be to the Scholler to trauel in, the night for him to reſt in: for by continuall labour are the eyes hurt, the wit dulled, the face in colour, and the bodie by ſwellings, and other diſeaſes thence growing, deformed and corrupted.</item>
                        <item>4 A reſolute determination, not to amend the things, which he liketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, without cauſe, which ſeemeth to be ſomewhat like the firſt poynt <hi>Orphëus</hi> here doth the contrarie, <hi>what late he liked, now he doth deteſt.</hi> For, a Scholler ought, vpon good reaſon ſhewed, to relinquiſh his owne vntrue, vncertaine, or worſer courſe, to followe the more certaine, and better courſe of another man.</item>
                        <item>5 Luſt, or vnlawfull loue, which comming of Sloath, is nouriſhed by exceſſe: and how can he entend to his ſtudie, or any other good medirations, who, as it is in <hi>Plautus,</hi> is like a wretch, vexed, troubled, and toſſed in the ſlaughter houſe of loue: who, where himſelfe is, his mind is not: where he is not, his mind is.</item>
                        <item>6 Too much ſleeping, which is called the brother of death, and as <hi>Menander</hi> ſaith, <hi>A patterne <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto men, and an image of death.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>7 Ouerliberall diet, or gluttonie, which is a beaſtlie vice in them, who like hogges, ſeeme to grunt out theſe words: <hi>We care not for Rumors, ſo that we may haue wherewith to fill the Rume.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:6"/>
                  <p>NESTOR his <hi>Antilochus: Poynting out the trueth and neceſſitie of Arte in</hi> ſtudie: by <hi>R. R.</hi> of <hi>Lyncolnes Inne,</hi> Student in the Common Lawes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Ridentem dicere verum </l>
                     <l>Quis vetat?</l>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Iuuenal.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>At London. 1587.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:7"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:7"/>
                  <head>NESTOR HIS Antilochus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I was come to reade this <hi>Proſopopey,</hi> wherin <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> the chiefe of <hi>Poëts,</hi> who is ſaid to bee accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the <hi>Muſes,</hi> was to make a ſpeach of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, fit to beſeeme the prudent King <hi>Nestor,</hi> called <hi>The Sheapheard of men,</hi> to giue to his owne ſonne, to the winning of a worthie prize, and with the prize re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, amongſt other Runners, noble Kings and Princes of <hi>Greece,</hi> which was by <hi>Achilles</hi> ordained, to the celebrating of the funerals of his deare friend <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troclus,</hi> hauing hungerlie taſted other of his pleaſant deuiſes, I conceaued hope, herewith to bee fed, euen, <hi>(Ad ſatietatem)</hi> to fulnes: <hi>Neque ſpes fallebat amantem.</hi> Theſe be the verſes:</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When prudent</hi> Neſtor, <hi>ſtanding neere his ſonne</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                           <hi>Wiſe like himſelfe: his counſaile thus begun.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Antilochus: <hi>becauſe, while but a lad</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Both</hi> Ioue <hi>and</hi> Neptune <hi>(louing thee full well)</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                           <hi>All horſemanſhip, which either of them had</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Haue taught thee: now I need not much to tell:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                           <hi>Yet though thou know the raynes to looſe and pull,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Be circumſpect withall, thine horſe be dull.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Their horſe indeed are farre</hi> 
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                           <hi>more ſwift, yet thou</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>With warie wit, maieſt counterpeize their pace:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Then all good councell take vnto thee now</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>My friend, to get the credite of the Race:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Carpenter by</hi> Arte <hi>doth bring to paſſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That feate, which flies the ſtrong, yet brainles Aſſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Againe, by</hi> Arte, <hi>the</hi> Pilot, <hi>he doth guide</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>On troubled Seas, his ſwift and toſſed barke:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>By</hi> Arte, <hi>the Couch-man knoweth how to ride:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To leaue his fellowe farre behind the marke.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The man, who truſteth to his horſe and Couch,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Full fraught with follie,</hi> 
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                           <hi>wandereth too much</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Amidſt the Race, and lets his horſes ſtray,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When, who knowes helpes, although his horſe be bad:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>An</hi> 
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                           <hi>eye vnto the marke, he ſtill doth lay,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And driueth cloſe, with pace,</hi> 
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
                           <hi>diſcreet, and ſad.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He raynning well, doth euermore</hi> 
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> 
                           <hi>obſerue</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The goale, from which, he</hi> 
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
                           <hi>careth, not to</hi> 
                           <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/>. <hi>ſwerue.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:8"/>
                  <p n="1">1 And firſt, whereas the <hi>Poët,</hi> ſuppoſeth the Hearer; to be wiſe like the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, he therein councelleth, that no precious ſtone be throwne before a Cocke, no learned ſpeach to be vttered to ſwiniſh men: <hi>Qui balbi, praeter balba, nihil intelligunt, &amp; palatum habent ſapientius quàm ingenium:</hi> who can better rel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh reaſons of the ſunne, than reaſons that proceed from men.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 For the Allegorizing hereof, from the particular vſe of <hi>Arte</hi> in riding, to the generall vſe thereof in Studying: leaſt I ſhould therein ſeeme to deale as auck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlie, as the Grammar Scholler did in his <hi>Simile: (Euen as a Ship is toſſed on the Sea, ſo ought a father to loue his child)</hi> it is to bee remembred, that by ſome learned, the <hi>Affections,</hi> which follow the Senſe, and are common to vs with beaſts, are likened to <hi>Horſes:</hi> The <hi>Hart</hi> and <hi>Braine</hi> wherein the Soule hath her chiefe reſidence, to the Seate of a Chariot, the whole bodie to a <hi>Chariot,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> the power of the <hi>Soule,</hi> to the <hi>Rider,</hi> which as with raynes keepeth back, or putteth forward the <hi>Affections,</hi> leaſt they being too dull, ſhould hinder from good: or too forwarde, ſhould leade both bodie and ſoule to hurt: whence ſeemes to be taken the raigning of Princes: for they being of a farther reach and entendment than the common ſort, do ſeeme no otherwiſe than the <hi>Rider</hi> doth the <hi>Horſe,</hi> than <hi>Reaſon</hi> doth the <hi>Affections,</hi> to excell in ruling the common people, who are numbred among the three euills: <hi>Ignis, mare, Populus, tria ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la.</hi> In concluſion the <hi>Allegory</hi> holding as before, I may tranſlate this verſe.</p>
                  <q>Fertur equis Auriga, nec audit currus habenas.</q>
                  <p>Thus:
<q>
                        <l>Affections doo beare the man away,</l>
                        <l>Which Reaſons Rule, will neare adeale obay.</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>Nestor</hi> graunting naturall wit and conſideration to his ſonne, and yet gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him counſaile, or knowledge of Arte, doth confirme that difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Conſideration and Prudence, which is taken by Sir <hi>Thomas Eliot,</hi> viz. Conſideration to be a bare conſiderance of the Cauſes, but Prudence to be with a conſideration, a continuance alſo of the Cauſes helping, and an auoydance of the Cauſes hindering, the atchieuing of the ends of our purpoſes: that one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more proper to youth, this other to age. For which reaſon, <hi>Antilochus</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing by ſleight, not by prudence, gotten the prize from the wiſe and aged King <hi>Menelaus,</hi> yet deiecting himſelfe, and acknowledging <hi>Menelaus</hi> his wiſedome, offereth him his gotten prize, with theſe words:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>O <hi>Menclaus,</hi> ſuffer now this wrong,</l>
                           <l>Your yeares are more, your wiſedome greater too</l>
                           <l>Than mine: for why, I am but very yong:</l>
                           <l>And youth (you know) doo many waies miſdoo.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>And though mine wit more readie be than thine,</l>
                           <l>Thy prudent counſaile ouerreacheth mine.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
Which modeſt confeſſion of <hi>Antilochus</hi> notwithſtanding, yet wiſedome is not alwaies in the gray haire, but in ſuch as doo ouercome their <hi>Affections,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that ſaying: <hi>Sedatis &amp; extinctis cupiditatum ardoribus, &amp; calore iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenili refrigerato, cum quadam tamen naturali probitate, ſeneſcere debent, qui ſapientiam inhiant.</hi> But now for the councell or knowledge of <hi>Arte,</hi> which I haue ſaid <hi>Nestor</hi> gaue vnto his ſonne, it is to be remembred that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is tranſlated <hi>Ars, Conſilium,</hi> or <hi>Prudentia,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>Coniugate</hi> thereof,
<pb facs="tcp:19109:8"/>
                     <hi>Artista, Conſiliarius,</hi> or <hi>Prudens.</hi> Now, if <hi>Arte</hi> and <hi>Counſaile,</hi> an <hi>Artiſt</hi> and a <hi>Counſailor</hi> be conuerted, it ſhould ſeeme, that a Councellor ſhould haue skill in <hi>Arte,</hi> eſpeciallie, for that, that our Lawes are knowne by the name of <hi>Iuriſpru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia,</hi> and <hi>Arte,</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> are ſignified by one and the ſame word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 I hope I ſhall not ſtretch the figure, if by the more ſwiftnes of <hi>Horſes,</hi> I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, a greater promptnes and alacritie of wit in ſome, than in other ſome. For by likening the <hi>Affections</hi> to <hi>Horſes,</hi> I entend all other naturall gifts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to vs with <hi>Beaſts,</hi> as <hi>Ingeny,</hi> in which the Foxe excelleth the Aſſe, and in which, ſome men exceed others naturallie, and yet they againe, by Arte &amp; good habite of them, whom they doo naturally excell for wit, are themſelues excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: which meaning I applie to this place. The excellencie of <hi>Arte,</hi> aboue natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall wit, may appeare by the euent of that controuerſie betweene <hi>Atax</hi> and <hi>Vliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> in penning whereof, <hi>Ouid,</hi> though in other matters he goeth beyond many other Latine Poets, yet therein he excelleth himſelfe: In which controuerſie, though he attribute vnto <hi>Aiax</hi> a good naturall wit, as appeareth in that, he vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, whatſoeuer might ſtand, to the ſetting out of his owne worthines, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring the leawd and cowardlie pranckes of <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> in extenuating thoſe deedes of <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> whereby he had gotten credite with the <hi>Graecians,</hi> yet <hi>Vliſſes</hi> by more skilfull and artificiall inſinuation with the Iudges, in vrging his own Acts with more modeſtie, and <hi>Aiax</hi> his faults more ſharplie, in extenuating his good deedes more cunninglie, and either paſſing ouer with ſilence, putting ouer to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or els auoyding fault with fault, one of his owne by obiecting another to <hi>Aiax,</hi> he got the Armour, which cauſeth the Poët to conclude. <hi>Mota manus procerum eſt, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>The Nobles, which were Iudges, did agree,</l>
                     <l>And then, what cunning could, a man might ſee:</l>
                     <l>The ſtrong mans harnes, was the wiſe mans ſee.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Which excellencie of cunning aboue wit and ſtrength, may alſo appeare by that part of <hi>Vliſſes</hi> his ſpeach, wherein he compareth himſelfe with <hi>Aiax,</hi> to this meaning:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>I doo foreſee, but thou without a minde</l>
                           <l>Bearſt ſtrength: thou knoweſt to fight, but I the fit</l>
                           <l>Seaſons for battaile, with <hi>Atrides</hi> finde:</l>
                           <l>Thou but in bodie: we excell in wit.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>How much the Pilot doth the Mariner,</l>
                           <l>How much the Captaine doth excell his man,</l>
                           <l>So much am I for policie thy better:</l>
                           <l>And of my bodie, by mine heart I can</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Performe by farre, more than I may by hand:</l>
                           <l>In inward parts doth all the glorie ſland.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which excellencie of wiſedome aboue ſtrength, may alſo appeare by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timent, wherewithall Maſter <hi>Martin Luther</hi> is ſaid to haue ieſted at thoſe Swa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouters,
<pb facs="tcp:19109:9"/>ſo called of their blacke Curtolles, wherewith they ſerued, and at ſuch other Launce Knights, who cutting their horſe tailes the beautie of horſes, ware feathers in their helmets (a feather and a penne, being in Latin ſignified by one word <hi>Penna</hi>) entending, that now Souldiours did ceaſe to take their glorie from ſtrength, which they defaced, and aſcribed the ſame to learning, which they ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunced.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 This <hi>Simile</hi> is herein excellent, becauſe (as I haue elſewhere ſhewed) <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zimmah,</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>Structura,</hi> ſignifieth alſo, <hi>Prudentia,</hi> or <hi>Dolus mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſus,</hi> no difference, being betweene <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Subtiltie,</hi> in the manner of doing, but in the purpoſe of the doer: So as <hi>Prudence</hi> being in the Hebrew tongue, ſo called of a building: the <hi>Simile</hi> ſeemeth good. I knowe not whether the ruling of the <hi>Magistrate</hi> may be ſaid of the <hi>Carpenter</hi> his <hi>Rule,</hi> wherewith he ordereth in iuſt meaſure and proportion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Pilot: Tully</hi> hath the ſame <hi>Simile,</hi> whereof <hi>Princes</hi> are ſaid, <hi>Clauum te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere Reipub.</hi> To ſterne the Common-wealth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That of the Couchman:</hi> is continued through the whole diſcourſe, and is commended as before.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 The mind may bee ſaid to bee beſides her gouernment, or to ſtray either by impotencie of nature, by euill habite, or by want of good habite: when the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is by nature, we call the man either a naturall, or an ideot. An Ideot, may be ſaid he, that exerciſing the phantaſie with idle contemplations, neuer diſcendeth to particulars. But, when this exerciſe is in iudgement vnto ſome certaine end, then is it no fault, but neceſſarie to ſtudie: for who was more famous amongſt the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> for any thing, than was <hi>Plato,</hi> called <hi>Diuinus,</hi> for his <hi>Idëa?</hi> which ſignifieth <hi>(originalis rerum ſpecies)</hi> or as <hi>Tully</hi> calleth it <hi>(ferè ſpecies)</hi> it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth therefore, if vniuerſalls be the beginnings of Studie: that they which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour almoſt wholly in particulars, goe not the neereſt way. If this vſe of the minde, be in Diuinitie, it is moſt commendable: for the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> are called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: for they do lift from earthly things, and therfore are called <hi>ſeparatae formae,</hi> and of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, commeth the verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to ſee, which is as commonlie ſpoken of the mind as of the Senſe: whence cunning men were ſometimes called <hi>Seers:</hi> and theſe make one part of <hi>Arte.</hi> But if this qualitie of the mind, in conſidering <hi>Vniuerſales</hi> do there reſt, not diſcending to particulars, the knowledge of which are the other part, or orderlie perfecting of <hi>Arte, Arte</hi> being of things alſo, and not all onely, of thoſe <hi>ſeparated formes:</hi> then is it ſaid of ſuch Schollers, that the greateſt Clarkes are not the wiſeſt men. That ſtraying of the minde, which commeth by euill habite, is either when a man is <hi>De non ſane memory,</hi> or <hi>non compos mentis:</hi> The firſt, when reaſon is vtterlie defaced, comming, either by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer labouring the minde, or by predominance of the affections, which make a man forget what he ſometimes was, or by cuill habite of the bodie, either in health, by defect, or ſuperfluitie of meates, defect of ſleepe, or by ſickneſſe. The other may come by the ſame meanes, but differeth in the manner, as being able which the other cannot) to ſpeake the trueth in manner of diſcourſe, but not in (the matter of diſcourſe, as of him, that would fetch ouer the old Moones, and would bring ouer Ilands, becauſe younger brothers wanted in <hi>England.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:19109:9"/>minde ſtraieth for want of good habite, either when wee are deceaued in the Principles, or in not exact conſidering of the particulars: or elſe when the mind hath not gotten the maſterie of the Affections, but reaſon yeeldeth, by reaſon of the continuall fight betweene the fleſh, and her Ruffians with the Soule, which is called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>The warre of nature,</hi> whence <hi>Ouid</hi> maketh <hi>Medea,</hi> being in loue with <hi>Theſeus,</hi> to diſpute her owne cauſe, thus, <hi>pro,</hi> and <hi>contra.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Shake off (if that thou mayſt) from maidens breſt</l>
                        <l>Theſe flames of loue, which thou doeſt entertaine:</l>
                        <l>Vnhappie, if I could, it were my beſt,</l>
                        <l>But this new force doth otherwiſe conſtraine:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And when that loue one thing perſwades me to,</l>
                        <l>Reaſon, another thing, would haue me do.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>Reaſon being at the laſt ouercome, ſhe thus concludeth.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I ſee the beſt, and doe allowe the ſame,</l>
                        <l>I follow bad.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p n="7">7 The <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> by an eye, looking foreright, in their <hi>Hierogliphikes,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokened <hi>Prudence:</hi> And thereto agreeth the common ſaying: <hi>Remember the end, and thou ſhalt not doo amiſſe:</hi> which I vnderſtand, to be ſpoken not onely concerning death, but alſo concerning the practizes of Studie.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Soft fire makes ſweete malt, and <hi>Soft</hi> and <hi>Sure,</hi> are the Prouerbes. The words in this place, are, <hi>Bouinis loris, An oxes pace:</hi> for <hi>Softnes Ennius</hi> commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>Fabius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>One man delaying, hath reſtorde our wealth,</l>
                     <l>Not prizing Rumors higher than our health.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p n="9">9 That the ſhame of being foyled, ought to bee a great encouragement to well doing, whence <hi>Nestor</hi> bidding his ſonne beware, leaſt in vnaduiſed dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, he ſhould wound his horſes and breake his Chariot, he addeth what would thence followe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Sport to thy fellowes, but a ſhame to thee,</l>
                     <l>Conſidering therefore, all ſo prudent bee.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Which in our purpoſe, differeth not much from that of <hi>Horace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Of idlenes contempt will growe in end:</l>
                     <l>Oh ſhame for me to liue without a frend.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And that of <hi>Virgil.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>He knowing his owne Vertues, Very ſhame</l>
                     <l>Doubled his ſtrength, and did his force enflame.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p n="10">10 Perſeuerance is councelled: which is hence noted in <hi>Antilochus,</hi> that when <hi>Atrides</hi> being offended, did counſaile him to driue after another manner than he did.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Antilochus, without regard or feare,</l>
                     <l>Droue faſter ſtill, as one that did not heare.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:10"/>
                  <p n="11">11 In generall, <hi>Arte</hi> is after one manner thus deſcribed, <hi>Ars eſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideratio ex finibus aſſumptis, Arte is the conſideration of cauſes from <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ends propounded:</hi> according vnto which, and orderlie conſideration muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the cauſes, as it is in this other deſcription of Arte, <hi>Ars eſt ratio, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; viam efficiens, Arte is reaſon, cauſing order and way:</hi> That is <hi>ordering, and making eaſie:</hi> So that from both theſe deſcriptions one more plaine may be drawne, which is this: <hi>Arte is an orderlie conſideration of the Cauſes from certaine ends propounded:</hi> For, that which in the latter is ſaide <hi>Reaſon,</hi> is here <hi>Conſideration: Order</hi> is included by his <hi>Coniugato; Orderlie; way</hi> is an effect and no efficient cauſe of Arte: for as a faire way is to a traueller, ſo is a way made by Arte, pleaſant to a Scholler.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:10"/>
                  <p>CERTAINE Generall Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions concerning the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Common Lawes, and that of the ſame there may be made a Science.</p>
                  <p> By R.R. &amp;c.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>Let no man ſeeke his owne, but euery man anothers wealth.</p>
                     <bibl>1. <hi>Cor. Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>verſ.</hi> 24.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>As when an Eunuch offereth violence to a Virgin, ſo doth he which abuſeth the Lawes.</p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>At London. 1587.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:11"/>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:11"/>
                  <head>Certaine generall Concluſions <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the condition of our</hi> Common Lawes.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>That of many imperfect Lawes, our Common Lawe, as hauing fewer imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, is moſt perfect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſhall be manifeſted by compariſon. Firſt, The Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> &amp; <hi>Perſians</hi> were of ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as that they might not be altered, whereby was taken away that Rule, which is the very Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowes of all Lawes. <hi>Quod inconſultò fecimus, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultò reuocemus:</hi> Like vnto theſe were the written lawes of the <hi>Athenians.</hi> It is ſaid of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> who (beſides our Common weale) are of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the world chieflie gouerned by Common Lawes of their owne: <hi>He that ſhall ſubſtanciallie conſider the manner of their proceedings, ſhall plainlie ſee that all matters are determined by the Iudges conſciences, and not by the Ciuill nor yet by their owne Lawes:</hi> but all good Lawes grounded vpon reaſon doo exerciſe a power ouer the Judge himſelfe, as ſhall be more plainlie ſhewed in the 9. Concluſion. Againe, it is ſaid of their Lawes, that in triall of matter vpon life and death, the partie himſelfe is neuer ſuffered to ſpeake, but he hath an aduocate for him, and the <hi>Auagadori</hi> againſt him: So that many times the perſon tarieth two, three, and ſometime foure yeares or euer he come vnto his triall of life and death. It is otherwiſe, and better in our Lawe, where the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is not onely ſuffered to ſpeake, but alſo diuers priſons haue bookes touching Plees of the Crowne, by which ſome of them during the time of their impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, become ſo cunning, as that they cannot onely iudge of their owne caſe, but alſo inſtruct others, whoſe caſes are different from theirs: beſides the Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or Gaole deliuerie are often times: ſo as the perſons are not long troubled with the feare of death, which is worſe than death it ſelfe. If wee ſhall compare our Lawe with the Ciuill Lawe, a learned Lawier Maſter <hi>Forteſcue</hi> hath giuen an inſtance, how in the Ciuill Law triall is by witneſſes onely, but in our Lawe by witneſſe and by the Countrey, where alſo it is lawfull by iuſt proofe to except againſt a witneſſe, and where the Iurie (if the action be locall, of lands or hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) is panelled, from, or as neere as may be to that Countie where the thing in controuerſie lieth: which is a ſpeciall poynt, in aſmuch, as in vaine are good lawes made, if that in triall they may be corrupted.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:12"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Accipe ſio legum errores, &amp; crimine ab vno,</l>
                     <l>Diſce omenes.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But our lawes, as the lawes of the famous Law-giuer <hi>Licurgus,</hi> are not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that is, they are not therefore lawes, becauſe that they are written, as thoſe of the <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Athenians,</hi> but they are yearely obſeruations vpon manners, as are our yeare-bookes: whence it is ſaid of the lawes of the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> and ſo likewiſe many be ſayd of our lawes: <hi>Lacedamonij verò, non jure ſcripto, ſed moribus tantùm vſu annorum comprobatis pro legibus vſe ſunt: Ideóque Locurgus leges ſcriptas Spartanis nullas dedit, ſed omnium conſcenſu, mores, tanquàm ſilex edita fuiſſet, experiundo obſeruárunt: hi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> adeò tenaces fuêre, vt omni ſcripto ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri anteïrent.</hi> So that hence may be gathered two extremities: one, in attributing too much vnto the writing, as thoſe of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> and of the <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians:</hi> another, in attributing too little to the writing, that is, to the written rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as thoſe lawes of the <hi>Venetians,</hi> betweene both theſe ſtandeth our lawe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther giuing too much to the lawe, which without good reaſon is written, nor taking any thing from that lawe which is written with good reaſon.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>That it is impoſsible that our Lawes, as they are now, ſhould be perfect.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>LIke as is the cauſe, ſuch is the effect: but man in his reaſon vnreformed, is imperfect, therefore cannot the lawes be perfected without Logique, which is a Reaſon reformed.</p>
                  <p>The waies of God are perfect with iuſtice in mercie, but the lawes of men are mercileſſe iuſtice, or rigor, whence the lawe is thus deſcribed: <hi>Lex eſt commune praeceptum, virorum prudentium, delictorum, quae ſponte vel ignorantia contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huntur coërtio, Reip ſponſio communis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Iuſtice, in regard of the imperfection and vntrueth of the precept, which no way can preiudice the perfection and trueth of Arte, is thus deſcribed: <hi>Iuſtitia eſt conſtans &amp; perpetua</hi> VOLVNTAS <hi>ſuum cuique tribuendi:</hi> And againe, <hi>Lex eſt ratio ſuum vnicuique tribuens, vel id ſaltèm</hi> AFFECTANS. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe that by the alteration of times, it may bee neceſſarie to alter the lawes.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 <hi>That though the Lawe in it ſelfe be rigorous and imperfect, yet as much as the common profite will ſuffer, it is made gentle, mercifull, and perfect by the Chauncerie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>FOr that is one end of that Court, and is therefore called a Court of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, becauſe it reaſoneth on the part of the Complaynant by <hi>Argument</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the law of nature <hi>Quod tibi fieri non vis alters ne feceris:</hi> &amp; hence alſo is it called <hi>Cancellaria quaſi Cancellans,</hi> as taking away &amp; anihilating the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of the Common Lawes: So is the Clients matter in the Common Law termed a Caſe, but in the Chauncerie a Cauſe: A Caſe it is termed becauſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the deſcription of <hi>caſus (caſus dicitur quandò prater efficientis ſcopum, nec neceſſariò, neque euidenti cauſa antecedente, aliquid accidit)</hi> the partie at the Common Law doth not of himſelfe know the reaſon or cauſe why it is by law adiudged with, or againſt him: but it is otherwiſe in the Chauncerie, where he is more able by light of nature to foreſee the end, and to giue a reaſon himſelfe of his cauſe or matter.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:12"/>
                  <p>The Iudge at the Common Lawe by reaſon maketh iuſt, or putteth a finite determination of the Lawe: but the Chauncerie adding nothing, it onely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth equall, that is, by the vſe thereof it tendeth more to a perfection: as when a Carpenter hauing cut his piller, doth not ſo leaue, but proceedeth to poliſh it: whence it is ſaid of the Iudge of the Common Lawe, <hi>Ratio ſtatuentis:</hi> and of the Iudge in the Chauncerie, <hi>Aequitas decernentis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Where note that the Lord, Chauncellor is entitled with a ſpeciall addition of diſcretion, becauſe that he ought ſo to relceue the caſe of a priuate perſon, as not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the prudence of the Law may be kept touching common profite, for better is it to ſuffer a miſchiefe to one man, than an inconuenience to the whole Common-wealth: and of this ballancing or diſcerning in cauſes may it be ſaid of the Lord Chauncellor, <hi>Qui ſub libra manſuetudinis, &amp; lenimento clementiae cuncta deliberat.</hi> Now, waying is not but of two ſeuerall matters; ſo as in one ſcale is the Common Lawe, in another Conſcience: yet not that the Common Lawe doth neuer ioyne with Conſcience, but becauſe that Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot euer in all caſes be joyned with the Common Lawes, and is by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſubtill practizes of common perſons to deceiue lawes: ſo that the Iudge cannot ſo circumſpectly pitch his hayes, but that theſe craſtie fellowes will finde cuaſions: for whereas Treſpaſſe is deſcribed thus, <hi>Tranſgreſsio eſt, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid prater modum fit:</hi> and the manner or meanes of doing being but ab <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> in outward things, and the Common Lawe hauing abilitie to ſee no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: ſuch ſubtill deuiſers, will ſo handle thoſe offences which they make, as the cauſes of the ſame reſting only inward in their hearts, the partie grieued ſhall be left remedileſſe at the Common Lawes: wherefore in this Court is the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter brought to light from out his conſcience: and as for a Foxe which like as a Beare or Wolfe, will not rudelie ruſh into euerie engyne made for his apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion this grin as proceeding of further purpoſe is ordained, as in caſe of a Pledge by <hi>Moſes</hi> lawes, the defendant was driuen to an oath to end controuerſies.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>That notwithſtanding the Lawes are imperfect, yet that of them ſo much as they are they may be made an Arte.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Becauſe that Arte maketh nothing but of things alreadie made, putteth a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct determination.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 <hi>That the Lawe though infinite in practize, is notwithſtanding finite in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>FOr that thing may be certaine, finite, and perfect in precepts, which is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, infinite, and imperfect in practize: and ſo do I deſire to be vnderſtood whereas I ſaid before of <hi>Reaſon</hi> that it was imperfect, wherby I meane, the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize of Logique, and ſo the practize of euery other Science: for I doubt not, but that there may be a perfect Logique. <hi>Ptolomey</hi> to this purpoſe putteth a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: <hi>Certa poſſunt eſſe, qua tamon ſunt infinita:</hi> which the Logitian (as I take it) expounding, ſaith, <hi>Rations certa ſunt, quae numero ſunt infinita:</hi> And to this purpoſe the Wiſeman himſelfe ſeemeth to affirme, ſaying, <hi>Mans wiſedome is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, and his knowledge in each Science vncertaine.</hi> But who knoweth not, that nothing is more proper to any thing, than certaintie is to a <hi>Science</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the precepts? therefore muſt this vncertaintie and this imperfection be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood
<pb facs="tcp:19109:13"/>of practize. The Lawyer ſaith of King <hi>E.</hi> 1. <hi>Quam juſte, quàm miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corditèr, quàm diſcretè erga ſubditos ſuos tempore pacis, pacis author, &amp; amator ſe habuit, non ambigitur: cùm tantae aequitatis ſit ſuae celſitudinis cura, quòd, in ca nullus judicum tàm attritae frontis, tàm temeraria ſit preſumptionis, quòd à ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiae tramite, aliquatènus declinare, aut aequitatis excedere praeſumat.</hi> By which ſpeach as he maketh it plaine, that the Law is an Arte, and ſo finite and perfect, ſo elſewhere, though calling the Lawe an Arte, yet comparing the ſame to the game at the Cheſts, he calleth it both infinite and imperfect, which we therfore muſt vnderſtand of the practize: as thus, <hi>Haec quidem ars arts luſili Scaccarij re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctè comparatur, tùm quod vtraque infinita eſt &amp; imperfecta, tùm quòd ſicut Rex, regem Scaccorum aſfuta quarit ſubtilitate mactare, ſic pars actrix litigád, vel diſrationando, reum nititur conuincere, redargutum ſua veritate, vel cautela.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, of God it is ſaid, that his waies are vnſearchable, and his pathes paſt finding out, therefore mans doings may bee ſought for, mans doings may bee found out. The Wiſeman ſaith that it is, <hi>The glorie of God to keepe a thing ſecret, but the Kings honor is to ſearch out a thing:</hi> It is a mans honor to bring a thing to light: as to make a Science of that which is obſcure: To giue ſome light that the lawes infinite in practize are notwithſtanding finite in principles and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: let it be thus. As the <hi>Phiſition</hi> hath finite <hi>Symples,</hi> and concerning them finite reaſons, of which <hi>Symples,</hi> though he doo make infinite Compounds, yet are they all prooued good or bad to that end whereunto they are prepared, by reaſons drawne from the finite Simples: So the Lawyer hath his finite elements, <hi>Acts, Perſons, Things,</hi> and their <hi>Adiuncts,</hi> and concerning them finite reaſons, of which though he compound Caſes infinite, yet are all thoſe caſes decided, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the finite reaſons of the finite elements.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 <hi>That ſuch Lawyers as affirme, that there is no ſcience of the Lawes, doe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that they profeſſe they knowe not what.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BEcauſe (that except the Law be wholly knowne) there may be ſomewhat in the lawe which not being in the Councellor his knowledge may alter the caſe. Beſides it is ſaid, <hi>Forma dat eſſe,</hi> becauſe that in all ſtudie wee ſtriue to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, which is a Science: therefore in that reſpect can no man be ſaid to know the ſame, except he knowe the ſame as a Science: For as a web of <hi>Arras,</hi> beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for diuerſitie of colours, goodlie for proportions, and profitable for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the ſtorie, is nothing ſo beautifull, nothing ſo goodlie, nothing ſo profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, when as it is mangled and cut in peeces: ſo the Lawe diſperſed here and there confuſedlie, is nothing ſo beautifull, nothing ſo goodly, nothing ſo profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, as if it were built vp in one Structure: Notwithſtanding, if a man knowe the whole lawe but for any one caſe, for ſo much he may be ſaid to haue the ſcience of the whole lawe.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 <hi>That for want of the ſcience of the Lawes, the Queene way ſometime looſe her right, what ſhe doth by lawe may be ſuſpected of wrong: Iuſtice may be corrupted in the Iudge and Officer, and the making of the lawes more perfect, greatlie hindered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>WIthout inſtance I will ſpeake in a generall manner, thus: becauſe that ſuch matters in lawe as are of one ſort, as well of the Crowne, as of right
<pb facs="tcp:19109:13"/>and title in land, of debt, of treſpaſſe, and of the caſe with the duetie and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of officers in iudgement, as alſo of the writs, and of the Acts of Practize, lye ſo confounded togither, as forgetfulnes &amp; neglect may cauſe ignorance through their miſorders: whereas by Arte an eaſie way is made to finde euerie thing, and that fullie and whollie in his proper place: for that is the effect of Arte: whence a learned man faith, that Arte worketh, <hi>Vt non ſit neceſſe quaerents, cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulorum numeroſit atem euoluere, cui, breuit as collecta, quod quaritur, offert ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne labore.</hi> And of Diuiſion, it is ſaid, <hi>Diuiſio animum legentis incitat, mentem intelligentiae praeparat, &amp; memoriam artificio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>è reforman.</hi> The Lawes (if in a Science) might bee greatlie perfected: becauſe that with better iudgement doo we apprehend and iudge of the effects of that thing which is compoſed and ſet vp before our eyes, than of that which is diſperſed, and is not all at once preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 <hi>That Logique is the instrument of the ſcience of the Lawe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Becauſe that it is the inſtrument of all Sciences.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 <hi>That any argument drawne from Diuinitie or humanitie (ſauing the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Law, wherein may be croſſed no rule of Diuinitie) is of forcible proofe, though there be no bookes for it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THis is prooued by the firſt definition of law: and he that ſhall denie a good argument ſo drawne for want of a booke, ſhall doo aſmuch as take away the Sunne, from which the Lawe as the Moone taketh her light: for the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples which are taken from the lawe of God, of nature and of reaſon, are many more than thoſe which are of Man, and are giuen by the abſolute diſcretion of the Iudge, and which doo concerne the prudence of the Lawe. And therefore hereunto may be applied that ſaying of a Lawyer: <hi>Leges autem Anglicanas, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cèt non ſcriptas, leges appellari, non eſt abſurdum: Si enim ob ſolum ſcripturae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum leges minimè cenſerentur, maioris procùl dubio auctoritatis robur, ipſis le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus videretur accommodare ſcriptum, quàm decernentis aequitas, aut ratio ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuentis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10 <hi>That though it require great practize to knowe the whole bodie of the Law and to order the ſame, yet may it being ordered and well opened be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difficultie vnderſtood of a man, which is no Lawyer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BEcauſe that to make eaſie is the end of Arte, and becauſe that it is eaſier (as experience teacheth) to vnderſtand many principles well put together, than to put many principles well together. So therefore may a man hearing the Lawe well deliuered, vnderſtand the ſame, though he doo not profeſſe the ſtudie of it.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 <hi>That whereof there is no reaſon giuen, that can be no Lawe, and ſo that the elder Lawe, if it haue the better reaſon, is the better Lawe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BEcauſe that the Lawe is nothing elſe but reaſon, and (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith) that <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> taketh her name <hi>à Venustate,</hi> not <hi>Venuſtas à venere,</hi> ſo may it be ſaid of
<pb facs="tcp:19109:14"/>the Iudge, that he taketh his name <hi>Iudex à Iudicio,</hi> not <hi>Iudicium à iudice. Rae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> he ſaith of the inartificiall argument, which is <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> whereof Lawe is a <hi>ſpecies, Argumentum in artificiale eſt, quod non ſua natura, ſed aſſumpta ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuius artificialis vi arguit: It aque cùm exquiſita rerum veritas ſubtiliùs exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur, perexiguam vim probationis habet: in ciuilibus autem, &amp; humanis rebus plerumqùe hoc argumentum praecipuam fidem è moribus arguentis efficit, ſi pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia, virtus, &amp; beneuolentia adfuerint.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12 <hi>That of the two, it were better the Lawes were bad, and the Lawyers good, than to haue good Lawes and bad Lawyers.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BY how much the efficient is more worthie than the effect: for a good Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer being a good man, of neceſſitie muſt make good Lawes, but not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertibly: for good Lawes are abuſed ſometimes by the practizes of the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors themſelues: whence is that ſaying, <hi>Meliùs gubernatur ciuitas ab optimo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, quàm ab optima lege.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Concluſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THat the Lawes (though in themſelues ſometimes too ſtrict) are qualified, and ſo though being imperfect, are perfected, and though imperfect yet may they bee made an <hi>Arte:</hi> though Caſes and their reaſons are vncertaine and infinite in practize, yet are they certaine and finite, in precepts: though hard at the firſt to bee knowne and ordered, yet being ordered, they may with more eaſe be vnderſtood by the <hi>Student,</hi> and by him being well opened may without great difficultie be vnderſtood by the Client.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19109:14"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHo knowes to plot the faſhion of a frame,</l>
                     <l>Albeit, it flatter not vnlearned eyes,</l>
                     <l>Tis like, can tell, how to ſet vp the ſame,</l>
                     <l>Through little chinkes, that who ſuch light eſpies,</l>
                     <l>Encouraging he haſteneth for an end</l>
                     <l>The good beginnings of a louing frend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>But wretched I, for ſight though not the worſt,</l>
                     <l>My feebled wits ſupporting ill their charge</l>
                     <l>Surcharg'd (alas) in chaſe by men accurſt,</l>
                     <l>(Whoſe honny mouthes their hidden wrongs enlarge)</l>
                     <l>As toyled Deere ſeekes ſhelter in the Towne,</l>
                     <l>Do flie thoſe curres, before you falling downe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For, well I knowe your helpe and fauour might</l>
                     <l>Be ſtaues, whereon my fainting Muſe ſhould guide</l>
                     <l>Such ſteps, that Error could not ſtrangle Right</l>
                     <l>Through ideot tongues, or hearts of helliſh pride:</l>
                     <l>Your Honor ſhall be rich in title then,</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Princes</hi> earſt, <hi>a foſterer of Men.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>Malum, patienti, Lucrum.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
